<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to the book of Sir Thomas Manwaringe of Pever in Cheshire baronet, entituled A defence of Amicia, daughter of Hvgh Cyveliok, Earl of Chester wherein is vindicated and proved that the grounds declard in my former book, concerning the illegitimacy of Amicia, are not envinced by any solid answer or reason to the contrary / by Sir Peter Leycester ...</title>
            <author>Leycester, Peter, Sir, 1614-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13568076</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13568076</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100342</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48364)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 462:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to the book of Sir Thomas Manwaringe of Pever in Cheshire baronet, entituled A defence of Amicia, daughter of Hvgh Cyveliok, Earl of Chester wherein is vindicated and proved that the grounds declard in my former book, concerning the illegitimacy of Amicia, are not envinced by any solid answer or reason to the contrary / by Sir Peter Leycester ...</title>
                  <author>Leycester, Peter, Sir, 1614-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 90 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mainwaring, Thomas, --  Sir, 1623-1689. --  Defence of Amicia, daughter of Hugh Cyveliok, Earl of Chester.</term>
               <term>Mainwaring, Amicia.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100342:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100342:1"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To the BOOK of Sir <hi>THOMAS MANWARINGE</hi> Of <hi>Pever</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> Baronet, ENTITULED A Defence of <hi>AMICIA</hi> Daughter of <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH CYVELIOK</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is Vindicated and Proved, that the Grounds declared in my former BOOK; Concerning the Illegitimacy of <hi>AMICIA,</hi> are not Evinced by any ſolid Anſwer or Reaſon to the contrary.</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>PETER LEYCESTER</hi> Baronet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100342:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100342:2"/>
            <head>TO Sir <hi>Thomas Manwaringe</hi> Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU are pleaſed to tell me in the Front of the Epiſtle before your Book, <hi>That it will appear ſtrange to thoſe that know the nearneſs of Blood betwixt us, that you ſhould appear in Print againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly I believe it is only the Zeal of your Opinion, touching the Legitimacy of <hi>Amicia,</hi> which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps hath taken but too deep a root within you, that makes you now endeavour to incline the World to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100342:3"/>be of your Opinion; and that the grounds alleadged in my Book (ſwaying my Reaſon to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Opinion) are no juſt grounds to ſupport it: But though we differ in Opinion, yet we may be loving Friends: for I hope we are <hi>Pii Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſarii,</hi> both Contending for the Truth rather then Victory: And therefore wiſh that we may be firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly united, as well in the bond of Friendſhip as Nature; and that as much as ever, without any Animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at all.</p>
            <p>And you tell me further, <hi>That if I would have been contented to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered what I did conceive concerning</hi> Amicia, <hi>as an uncertainty only</hi> (<hi>as I have done that of</hi> Roger, <hi>Son of the ſaid Earl</hi> Hugh) <hi>I know you would have reſted ſatisfied, without giving me or the Reader the trouble of any one of your Lines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſay, I remember well you moved me to have put <hi>Amicia</hi> under the head or notion of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100342:3"/>doubtfull Iſſue of Earl <hi>Hugh;</hi> at which time I told you, I muſt either put her under the Title of Lawful Iſſue, or Unlawful Iſſue; for there was no <hi>Medium:</hi> She muſt certainly be either Lawful, or Unlawful, if any Daughter at all: And I thought it not fit to put down in my Book any third Title of Doubtful Iſſue: But till now, I never underſtood you would be content with the words which I put down concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Roger</hi> Son of the ſaid Earl; for elſe (if I know my own mind) I ſhould certainly have gratified your deſire therein. For in the next Page of my Book, I ſay, I ſhall then add the Reaſons why I conceive her to be a Baſtard; which is the very Expreſſion that I uſed to the reſt.</p>
            <p>There are yet two or three things in your Epiſtle, which in the firſt place I deſire to obſerve unto you.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>That you ſay, you very much wonder when I mention</hi> Raufe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100342:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100342:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100342:5"/>Manwaringe <hi>Chief</hi> 
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">I apprehend not why you call him chief Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> when in thoſe Ages there was onely one Judge of <hi>Cheſter</hi> at a time.</note> 
               <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>and his Son</hi> Roger, <hi>and</hi> William Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waringe <hi>younger Son of the ſaid</hi> Roger, <hi>that I take not notice that they were all three Knights; becauſe I had ſeen Proofs thereof by many Deeds, where the word</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus <hi>is prefixed to each of their Names; which was not (that you know of) uſed to be done to any in thoſe elder Ages, but thoſe that were Knights, Clergy men only excepted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am very confident, that it was applied alſo to the better ſort of Gentlemen in thoſe Ages, who were no Knights; nor is it a ſure Rule to be always underſtood of a Knight, unleſs the word <hi>Miles</hi> do follow; and in thoſe elder Ages it was ſometimes prefixed, and oftener omitted, even to the ſame men; as <hi>Domino Galfrido de Dutton,</hi> who in the Original Chart of <hi>Nether-Tabley</hi> writes himſelf onely — <hi>Ego Galfri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus de Dutton dedi, &amp;c.</hi> and ſeveral other Deeds I have ſeen of the ſame
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100342:5"/>Perſon (who was lineal Anceſtor to <hi>Warburton</hi> of <hi>Arley</hi>) wherein I dare affirm among the Witneſſes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, he hath five times and more the word <hi>Dominus</hi> omitted, for once that we find it prefixed to his Name; and am very confident was not in him, as many others alſo, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued any more then Maſter <hi>Geffrey Dutton,</hi> and that he was no Knight; for when the Party makes a Deed, he will uſually uſe what Title he hath, eſpecially if he be a Knight (for Eſquires in thoſe Ages were none, which came not to be added in old Deeds till after the Statute of Additions under <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it was firſt made a diſtinct Title under <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond) he will be loath to looſe that Title: whereas Subſcription of Witneſſes, which are put by the Writer of the Deed, many times have ſome diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the better ſort of Gentlemen from the reſt by the word <hi>Domino;</hi> which word is never uſed in old Deeds by the Party himſelf, but where it is joyned with another
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100342:6"/>word, as <hi>Ego Willielmus Manwaringe Dominus de Peever;</hi> ſo alſo in your Book, <hi>p.</hi> 70. where it is ſo uſed — <hi>Ego Robertus Dominus Moaldiae;</hi> for <hi>ipſa vox (Dominus) primo de Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratore, poſtea de Rege, demum de quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis Territorii Domino enunciata fuit: Spelmanni Gloſſarum, p.</hi> 182. <hi>b.</hi> And in Subſcriptions it is very uncertain; ſometimes added, and ſometimes not added: And ſo are the placing of the Witneſſes in thoſe Subſcriptions of elder Ages very uncertain alſo; for we may obſerve that the ſame men, being Witneſſes to ſeveral Deeds, are many times one put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other in one Deed, and the ſame put after the other in another Deed: As to the word <hi>Dominus,</hi> if you pleaſe to look back on thoſe your Anceſtors mentioned in thoſe Deeds put down in your Book, as <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>Radulfus de Meidnilwaringe Omnibus, &amp;c.</hi> you have here no Title uſed, and yet this was after <hi>Bertrey</hi> his Daughter was marriageable; but you will ſay, poſſibly that was before he was Juſtice of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> ſee then <hi>p.</hi> 70.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100342:6"/>
               <hi>Teſtibus Radulfo de Menilwarin. tunc Juſticiario Ceſtriae, &amp;c.</hi> without any <hi>Domino</hi> prefixed; and very many others I have ſeen alſo, where he is ſo Subſcribed; look but into your own Deeds diligently, and tell me if you find not many more Subſcriptions mentioning <hi>Roger Manwaringe,</hi> and <hi>William Manwaringe,</hi> without the word <hi>Domino</hi> then with it; and not any Writing thus, either <hi>Ego Rogerus,</hi> or <hi>Ego Willielmus Manwaringe Miles;</hi> ſee alſo <hi>p.</hi> 69. where moſt of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are put with <hi>Domino</hi> prefixed; and <hi>p.</hi> 70. the next Deed following, <hi>Raufe Manwaringe</hi> then Juſtice, <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Maſcy, Guarin Vernon,</hi> and <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Venables</hi> (who are all Witneſſes to the other Deed) are in this put down without <hi>Domino</hi> prefixed; nor is there any one in this Deed, which hath <hi>Domino</hi> prefixed: So that it is plain it was ſometimes added by the Clearks, and ſometimes not added at pleaſure: and alſo uſed to the better ſort of Gentlemen who were no Knights, as well as to Knights and Clergymen: And at this day, as the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100342:7"/>word [Sir] is in common Diſcourſe applicable to Perſons of Quality from the higheſt to the loweſt in it's larger notion, ſo <hi>Dominus</hi> is applicable to any Knight or Gentleman; as if I ſhould ſay, <hi>Domine, quaeſo, num hoc verum eſt quod dico, necne?</hi> but in this thing here ſpoken of, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you did mention it to me; and I fully intended to have called them all Knights, but I know not by what Fate it was forgotten; whether by my intentneſs on more weighty things to amend them before my Book went to the Preſs, or my Book having been now above a year and a half out of my hands ſince I ſent it away from me, it ſeems I loſt the opportunity and forgot it; and I had rather give to any, eſpecially to your family; more then is due, then leſs; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it is not poſſible for me to place my words ſo in every particular, as can give all men content.</p>
            <p>Again you tell me, <hi>That you might take notice of my miſtake in my Book,</hi> p. 336. <hi>where I blame the Herald who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100342:7"/>in Queen</hi> Elizabeth's <hi>time made for the then Sir</hi> Randle Manwaring's <hi>Coat, Barry of twelve Peeces Argent and Gules; for which I cited</hi> Guillim's <hi>Heraldry; but that was the miſtake of</hi> Guillim, <hi>not the Herald; for that which the Herald did then allow (which I Blazoned amiſs) was Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, ſix Barrulets Gules</hi> — <hi>And the</hi> Manwarings <hi>of</hi> Pever (<hi>now next heir Male to</hi> Manwaringe <hi>of</hi> War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mincham) <hi>have a good right to the ſix</hi> Barrulets <hi>with which Sir</hi> Roger Manwaringe <hi>did Seal, as well as they have to the two Barres which Sir</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Manwaringe <hi>of</hi> Warmincham <hi>did bear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here is the Herald's errour, that it ſhould be given by him to <hi>Manwaringe</hi> of <hi>Pever</hi> now in theſe late Ages as his moſt proper Coat; whereas ever ſince the time of the ſaid Sir <hi>Roger Manwaringe,</hi> as well the Heirs of the right Line, as alſo the <hi>Manwarings</hi> of <hi>Pever</hi> (after they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came next Heir-Male) have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly born the two Barres for ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100342:8"/>hundreds of years without alteration ſucceſſively, and not the ſix Barru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets at all till this Change of the Herald in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> time: why now, though the Poſterity of Sir <hi>Roger</hi> might have continued the right of ſix Barrulets, yet they chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſame to two Barres which after ſo many Ages hath now gained an Hereditary right; for at firſt Coats were aſſumed at Pleaſure; but from <hi>Henry</hi> the Third's time downward Arms began to be made Hereditary; and moſt Gentlemen from that time downwards did bear the Coat of their Anceſtors, as it were heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily; and here is the Abſurdity, that the Herald alters the Coat again to ſix Barrulets, after ſo many Ages paſt, when the two Barres had been ſo long retained as an Hereditary right; for let any man but imagine what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion Changes would make, in caſe every Son ſhould vary from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by bearing a diſtinct Coat, and ſtick to no certainty: wherefore it ſeems abſurd, and I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it may deſtroy a right already
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100342:8"/>gained in this Caſe; for it is uſage onely that makes a right herein, as you may ſee in the great Suit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Scroop</hi> and <hi>Groſvenour,</hi> in the Marſhall's Court under <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, concerning the bearing of a Coat of Armes, whereto both chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged a right and Property by Uſage, but no other way.</p>
            <p>And thirdly you tell me, <hi>That you ſuſpect I have branded ſeveral Perſons in my Book with Baſtardy, without direct Proof thereof; and although you concern not your ſelf for any, but ſome of thoſe by me mentioned, when I write of the baſe Iſſue of</hi> Hugh Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veliok; <hi>yet if you make it appear that I have there without any certainty aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed two other Ladies beſides</hi> Amicia, <hi>you hope I ſhall have no juſt Cauſe to blame you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly I ſhall not, For thoſe you hint upon, but name not, I can make no anſwer to take off your ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, till I know who they be; but the other two Ladies beſides <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100342:9"/>I conceive you mean <hi>Geva</hi> Daughter of <hi>Hugh Lupus,</hi> and the Wife of <hi>Bacun</hi> Daughter of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok;</hi> which two you bring in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of <hi>Amicia:</hi> for thoſe being proved Baſtards, will be a great blow to <hi>Amicia;</hi> and had not the Caſe of <hi>Amicia</hi> been concerned, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve theſe two had never been ſpoken of by you, nor ſuſpected nor doubted of: But if I do make good what I have Alledged, I hope then you will recant for branding me with an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion; which I think I ſhall do, with as much certainty as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing and times will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</p>
            <p>So much touching your Epiſtle: and now I proceed to the reſt of your Book.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100342:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 21, 22.</p>
            <p>WHere in the firſt place you wonder, <hi>That I ſhould ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily call</hi> Amice <hi>a baſe Daughter of</hi> Hugh Cyveliok, <hi>unleſs I had more ſure grounds to go upon; and though it be your Taske onely to defend</hi> Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, <hi>yet you ſuppoſe you ſhall make it appear before you have done, that I go on no abſolute certainty, in calling</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun's <hi>Wife, Mother of</hi> Richard Bacun <hi>Founder of</hi> Rouceſter-Priory, <hi>another baſe Daughter of</hi> Hugh Cyveliok, <hi>or in calling</hi> Geva <hi>a baſe Daughter of</hi> Hugh Lupus: <hi>and then you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind me of what I have been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told, that thoſe Heralds that gave</hi> Manwaringe <hi>of</hi> Pever <hi>the Quartering of the Earl of</hi> Cheſter's <hi>Coat in Queen</hi> Elizabeth's <hi>time, were Mr.</hi> Cambden, <hi>and Mr</hi> Erdeſwick, <hi>Perſons that you do not know why I ſhould ſo much miſlike their boldneſs and ignorance (as I call it) for their ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100342:10"/>
            <p>Whereunto I ſay, My grounds are certain enough to prove them all three Baſtards, and ſuch as yet is not refelled by you, by any ſubſtantial Anſwer to the contrary, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Looſe it will ſo appear; as to the Heralds you mention, you ſay you would remind me that you had formerly told me of them; but you never told me till long time after that part of my Book was written; what then? Mr. <hi>Cambden</hi> I hold a moſt Learned man, and one of the beſt Antiquaries of our Nation in this laſt Age; but yet for doing this thing, whether <hi>Cambden</hi> himſelf, or who ever elſe, I ſay he was overbold in it, and it is erroneous; for though in the Age of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second Quartering of Coats was not in uſe, yet about the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, every Gentleman began to Quarter the Coat of the chief Heir with whom his Progenitor had match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and after <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth's time, marſhalling of many Coats to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether came into uſe, and this was to ſhew their right; ſo ſaith <hi>Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100342:10"/>himſelf in his Remains, <hi>p.</hi> 225. of the Edition thereof put out by <hi>Philpot.</hi> Now between the Age of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth and Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> had elapſed above 150. years, time enough to have taken notice of ſuch a Quartering, if it had been right and due; but you ingeniouſly confeſs in the place cited, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in ſtrictneſs it may be true, that it doth only belong to thoſe of the whole-blood to Quarter Coats, and that to ſhew their rights; yet it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now a common practice for thoſe of the Half blood to do it, you know not why it ſhould be accounted a crime in your Family more then in others in the like Caſe: True, it is as lawful in your Caſe as any other, if your Caſe be the ſame with others: I ſay, the Quartering of the Coat of a Coheir ought not to be given by any Herald to any, but the Coheir of the Whole-blood; which in ſtrictneſs, you do confeſs; Is not that Herald then to be miſliked, both for his boldneſs and errour, who ſhall at any time give it to the Half-blood? but in this Caſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100342:11"/>I believe it will not appear to be given to the Half-blood, as you call it; unleſs it be meant of a Half-blood illegitimate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>Becauſe</hi> Manwaringe <hi>was not an equal Competitor to the Coheir of the Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>could be no ſubſtantial Argument to prove</hi> Amicia <hi>Illegitimate; and ſo you paſs to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate your Anceſtour to have been ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed of a good Eſtate of Lands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto I ſay, I do not urge that for an Argument of her Illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, we ſhall come to that anon. I only there obſerved chiefly, that ſhe was no Coheir, which you grant; and therefore the Herald ought not to have given to <hi>Manwaringe</hi> the Quartering of the Earl of <hi>Cheſter's</hi> Coat at all; which you do grant to be in ſtrictneſs true, and which I have touched immediately before; and I ſhall likewiſe grant your Family to be a Family of good Quality, both
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100342:11"/>at that time, and at this preſent alſo; I ſhould be loth to ſay to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: but as to your note of Dukes and Earls to have been anciently Judges of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> you ſhould have diſtinguiſhed of the times; for that was not till the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second (who made Deputies to act in their ſtead) before which time you find no ſuch great Perſons Judges there; nor from <hi>Henry</hi> the Seaventh's time downwards.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Page</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>The caſe was not the ſame with the other Daughters of the Earl of</hi> Cheſter, <hi>when</hi> Rafe Manwaringe <hi>married</hi> Amicia, <hi>as it was afterward; for</hi> Amicia <hi>was married in the life time of her Father Earl</hi> Hugh; <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as thoſe four came to be ſuch great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes upon the death of their Brother</hi> Randle <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter <hi>and</hi> Lincolne <hi>without Iſſue, to whom they then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Heirs, they being his Siſters of the Whole-blood; and though all or moſt of them were married before they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100342:12"/>became to be his Heirs, yet the ſaid Earl</hi> Randle <hi>having never had Iſſue, the expectation of that Eſtate added to their other Fortunes, muſt needs make them very conſiderable Fortunes; whereas</hi> Amicia <hi>was but of the Half-blood, being a Daughter of Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>by a former Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein firſt you beg the Queſtion, which was never granted, nor can ever be proved, That <hi>Amicia</hi> was of the Half-legitimate Blood to Earl <hi>Randle</hi> by a former Wife of Earl <hi>Hugh:</hi> but <hi>dato hoc, ſed non conceſſo:</hi> It is more rational to imagine, that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> matching his only Daughter by a former Wife (as you ſuppoſe) in his life-time, would have married her to as conſiderable a Perſon, as was either provided by himſelf, or his Son, for his younger Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by a ſecond venter, whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation (which you conceive added to their Fortunes, whereby they matched to ſo great Perſons) could
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100342:12"/>not be much, being grounded upon great uncertainties, ſince it could not be foreſeen (when they married) that their Brother ſhould dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Iſſue, who afterwards married two Wives ſucceſſively, purpoſely to have Iſſue of his own Body to inherit his own Lands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>That I acknowledge I have been informed that three eminent Judges, and four Heralds, are of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that <hi>Amice</hi> was Legitimate; and was alſo told lately by one, whom you hope I have no reaſon to diſcredit, that ſince then ſeveral other Judges and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds have been conſulted; all which did concur in the ſame Opinion, that</hi> Amicia <hi>was no Baſtard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto I anſwer and confeſs, I was ſo informed; but it was you your ſelf who informed me; nor did I ever yet ſee any Opinion under
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100342:13"/>their hands, nor their grounds and reaſons for ſuch their Opinions at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted: what can be made of this? Let the ingenious Reader judge of the Argument: ſome Judges and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds are of that Opinion, <hi>Ergo</hi> ſhe was Legitimate. In theſe Caſes all that can be ſaid <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con</hi> ſhould have been put indifferently on both ſides, when any grave Perſon is to be conſulted; which hitherto hath been done privately on the one ſide one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without hearing the Reaſons on the other ſide; and you know how Opinions are not rarely given accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the putting of the Caſe, but very frequent and uſual; when many times even the Lawyers themſelves differ in their Opinions: But I can compare this to be like nothing more then going about to get hands to a Petition or Certificate. It is not Opinions that ought to ſway the Judgment of all indifferent Readers, but ſolid Reaſon. And I ſhall deſire to be Confuted with ſubſtantial Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, not Opinions of this or that man.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100342:13"/>
            <p>And now I come to your Reply a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Anſwers given to the Arguments for <hi>Amicia,</hi> which I ſhall fully comprehend in ſhort, that the Reader may with leſs trouble better apprehend the Point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 30, 31.</p>
            <p>Where you ſay, <hi>That my Anſwer is, that it is true, the Law is ſo taken at this day;</hi> i. e. <hi>that Lands cannot paſs</hi> in libero maritagio <hi>with a Baſtard: but I doubt whether it was ſo taken in the elder Ages of</hi> Henry <hi>the Second, and upwards: and alſo that I cite</hi> Glanvil <hi>Chief Juſtice of</hi> England, <hi>who lived in the time when</hi> Amicia <hi>lived: and that I do alſo ſhew you a Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, where Lands were given by the Father in free Marriage with his baſe Daughter: and I ſay further, that the Common Law in ſundry other things is at this day altered from what it was in former Ages, long after the time of</hi> Henry <hi>the Second;</hi> for which I cite
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100342:14"/>Cooke <hi>upon</hi> Littleton <hi>in ſeveral places:</hi> Theſe are my words.</p>
            <p>Your Reply, <hi>Pag.</hi> 30, 31.</p>
            <p>Hereunto you reply to what I urge out of the Lord <hi>Cooke; That you conceive the Common Law, where not altered by Parliament, is the ſame at this day that it was formerly: and you cite</hi> Cooke <hi>upon</hi> Littleton, <hi>p.</hi> 115. b. (<hi>which ſhould have been</hi> fol. 115. b.) who ſaith, <hi>It is a Maxime of the Law, That whatſoever was at the Common Law, and is not ouſted or taken away by any Statute, remaineth ſtill; and ſo conſequently you argue, that if it ever were the Common Law, that Lands or Services might paſs</hi> in libero mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagio <hi>with a Baſtard, or one that is not of the Bloud, it would be lawful to do ſo ſtill; becauſe that part of the Law is not ouſted or taken away by any Statute:</hi>—<hi>So that the places which I have cited, do not prove, That the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law at this day doth vary from what it was in former Ages in any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; but only that it was taken to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100342:14"/>be otherwiſe in thoſe dayes: just like ſome Caſes in our Reports, which at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times have been adjudged directly contrary to each other; but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Law was ſtill the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I Anſwer; Firſt, To the Maxime of Law, wherein it is ſaid, <hi>that whatſoever is not ouſted or taken away by any Statute, remaineth ſtill;</hi> wherein the word <hi>Ouſted</hi> muſt needs be underſtood disjunctively, or conjunctively: if disjunctively, then the words <hi>(not ouſted)</hi> muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of ſome other way than by Statute; and then it is as much as to ſay, <hi>not altered:</hi> and ſo implies a common practice of the Law, in ſuch caſes, contrary to what it was formerly. If it be underſtood con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctively, then the words muſt needs bear this ſence; that the Law is the ſame ſtill in all points as it was before, except where taken away by Statute: And thus underſtood, I ſhall produce you <hi>Cooke</hi> againſt <hi>Cooke,</hi> in his Book
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100342:15"/>upon <hi>Littleton,</hi> fol. 34. §. 39. His words are theſe—<hi>In ancient time it appeareth by</hi> Glanvil, <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>it was taken</hi> (that is, the Law was taken) <hi>that a man could not have endowed his wife</hi> ad oſtium Eccleſiae <hi>of more than a third part; but of leſs he might: but at this day the Law is taken as</hi> Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>there holdeth; which is, that a man may endow his wiſe</hi> ad oſtium Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae <hi>of his whole Land, or of the half, or other leſs part.</hi> So that here we ſee the Law in this caſe is altered, and without any Statute; <hi>ergo</hi> the Law is altered without any Statute. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Ibid.</hi> fol. 8. a. towards the bottom, —<hi>Of ancient time the Heir was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to have an Action of Debt upon a Bond made to his Anceſtor and his Heirs; but the Law is not ſo at this day:</hi> But herein was no Statute made to take it off; <hi>ergo,</hi> the Law in that caſe is altered without any Statute: And ſo in many other Particulars, which might be here cited; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore methinks it is the better expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Maxime, that the words be underſtood disjunctively; and ſo
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100342:15"/>it thwarts not with that which the Lord <hi>Cooke</hi> ſaith in theſe other places: and the word <hi>(or)</hi> is meerly a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctive.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Second Reply,</hi> p. 31, 32.</p>
            <p>But you go on and ſay, <hi>you would come as near me as you can; and you acknowledge, that though the Common Law was ever the ſame, where not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by Parliament; yet in former ages they did in ſome Particulars take the Law to be atherwiſe than they now do: and if I could prove that they did ſo in caſe of free-marriage, it would take off your Argument; becauſe the ancient Deeds and Grants are to be expounded as the Law was taken to be at the time of the Grant; as</hi> Cooke <hi>upon</hi> Little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>ſaith,</hi> fol. 8. b. <hi>For ſay you, that if it had been taken in former ages, that Lands might have been given in free-marriage with a Baſtard, or one not of the bloud, it would have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly been obſerved by ſome of the Sages of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100342:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer to your Second Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray you, if in former Ages the Law was taken otherwiſe in ſome particulars, than at this day it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: which hath now joyned (to ſtrengthen it) the common practiſe of the Nation (which I take to be the Common Law at this day) for many Ages together, without any contradiction; what rational man can deny, but the Law in ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars is clearly altered? For in thoſe Caſes (I ſpeak not of any altered by Act of Parliament) I would ask you whether the Law be now altered or no? If it be altered, then you are in an errour, to ſay the Law remains the ſame; and if it be not altered, then the former Law is ſtill our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, and not the Common Law as at this day it is taken; which is uſed otherwiſe at this day than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly: Then our Common Law in the particular caſes mentioned, and at this day uſed otherwiſe than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, is no Common Law of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:100342:16"/>becauſe (ſay you) the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law cannot be altered without an Act of Parliament, but remaineth ſtill the ſame; and ſo the Judges of <hi>England</hi> in all theſe caſes, at this day do not judge aright according to our Common Law: I pray you, ſee what abſurdities follow hereupon: And as to proving of Lands to have paſſed in free-marriage with a Baſtard in the Age of <hi>Amicia,</hi> I have already given you a Precedent for it; and the Lands did paſs accordingly: and ſhall make it good (when I come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it in its proper place) that <hi>Geva</hi> was certainly a Baſtard, by as good proof as poſſibly can be expected in ſuch a Caſe: But more of this, when I come to <hi>Geva.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your third Reply, pag.</hi> 33.</p>
            <p>In the next place, you have a long Harangue from <hi>p.</hi> 33, to <hi>p.</hi> 41. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you endeavour to reſtrain the words of <hi>Glanvil,</hi> which are theſe, —<hi>Quilibet liber homo quandam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem terrae ſuae cum filia ſua, vel cum
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100342:17"/>aliqua alia qualibet muliere, dare po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test in maritagium:</hi> and firſt, you begin to prove it by Scripture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. where a Liberty was given to the <hi>Jews</hi> to eat whatſoever their ſoul deſired; and yet this muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of ſuch meats as were legally clean and allowed them by the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer to your third Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſeldom known, nor I believe any other, any ſuch Queſtion as this, whether <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> had a former wife, to be proved by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Scripture, or Nicety of Law; which is meerly a Queſtion of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: For the Text urged by you, <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.26. I find no ſuch general Latitude, which needs any Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as you mention: The words are, —<hi>Thou ſhalt beſtow that money for whatſoever thy ſoul lusteth after, for Oxen, or for Sheep, or for Wine, or for ſtrong drink, or for whatſoever thy Soul deſireth.</hi> The Text is clearly reſtringent to thoſe things here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, which they were allowed to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100342:17"/>eat and drink according to their Law. What is this to the point in hand? <hi>ergo Glanvil</hi>'s words, <hi>Cum aliqua alia qualibet muliere,</hi> muſt be underſtood to be agreeable to the Law of the Land where he lived; that is, (as you would have it) to any except a Baſtard, or a Woman not of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors bloud: But how doth that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be the Law in <hi>Glanvil</hi>'s time or upwards? <hi>He was the firſt who redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced our Law into writing: Omnium pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>reddere aggreſsus est,</hi> ſaith <hi>Spelm.</hi> in his Gloſſ. <hi>p.</hi> 333. And it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to obſerve how lame and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect our Law was in thoſe times, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards what it was in <hi>Littleton</hi>'s time; and eſpecially compared with theſe laſt ages: But in ſhort, your Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions all along to <hi>pag.</hi> 41. by <hi>Bracton,</hi> or <hi>Fleta,</hi> or others, or making <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> to fight with himſelf, unleſs <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>'s words be interpreted as you would have them, I leave to wiſe men to judge, who will take pains to ſcan them, whether they be perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. For that wherein you ſay <hi>Glanvil</hi> contradicts himſelf, becauſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100342:18"/>he ſaith, <hi>that none can give Lands</hi> in remunerationem Servitii ſui <hi>to hold good after the death of the Donour;</hi> what is this to the point, why a man cannot give his Lands to any <hi>in libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro maritagio?</hi> or that it was not uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in thoſe dayes to paſs Lands in free marriage with a Baſtard, calling her only his Daughter, without the addition of Baſtard, and thereby, owning her to be of his bloud and kindred? The ſum is this; The Lawyers of latter ages do expound the Law, That Lands cannot paſs in free marriage with Baſtards; <hi>ergo</hi> it was ſo taken in <hi>Glanvil</hi>'s time, and his words muſt be ſo underſtood, though he ſay no ſuch thing: This is a great <hi>Non ſequitur.</hi> And yet our Lawyers ſay now, Baſtards are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of receiving Lands after they have gained a Name by reputation; which <hi>Amicia</hi> had gained; as we ſee in the Deed, where ſhe is called and owned by the Earl for his Daughter: But you tell me in the Cloſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 41. That the Common Law hath alwaies been the ſame, becauſe <hi>Cooke</hi> on <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleton</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:100342:18"/>ſaith, That <hi>the Comon Law hath no Controller but an Act of Parliament:</hi> which I have told you, muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, whilſt it remains the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law; which yet may alter, and hath altered, in ſundry Particulars, without any Act of Parliament; as I have before proved.</p>
            <p>But here I muſt turn you back to <hi>p.</hi> 12, <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. where this hath been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently anſwered before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 42. <hi>Your Fourth Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>There is not any weight in what I ſay,</hi> viz. That it ſeems to me in thoſe elder ages Baſtards were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted of the Bloud, by the frequent Appellation of them by the names of Unkle, Brother, Daughter, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for by the ſame reaſon I ſhould repute them of the bloud now, this Age being as Civil to them in their expreſſions, as any Age could poſſibly be.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:100342:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But where do you find almoſt in any Deeds of theſe laſt Ages, where ſuch are not now called Baſtard-ſons, Baſtard-daughters, Baſtard-brothers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in all Settlements and Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of Annuities or Portions; which in the very ancient Ages was never uſed: Nay, what ſay you, if I affirm they be of the Bloud both now and in former Ages? though the Law will not allow them ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they now are eſteemed in the eye of the Law <hi>quaſi nullius filius;</hi> for if A. have a Baſtard ſon or daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which is really his; they muſt needs be of his bloud: For no Law can extinguiſh Nature; though by the Common Law they are not now eſteemed ſo. And what if I ſay, that the reaſon why in the Deeds of thoſe elder Ages they were called Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters without any addition of Baſtard, whereby the Party owned them to be of their Kindred and Bloud, was, that the Inheritance of the Lands
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100342:19"/>paſſed in <hi>libero Maritagio</hi> with ſuch, might deſcend to their heirs? For our Lawyers now tell us, that Baſtards are capable of receiving Lands after they have gained a Name by Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; why may not then Baſtards, having gained the Names of Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, receive a Grant from their own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Fathers, either in Frank-marriage, or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>And now you come to <hi>Geva,</hi> and my Precedent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 43.</p>
            <p>For the Precedent I have given, wherein (I ſay) Lands were given <hi>in libero maritagio,</hi> you conceive it will not hold; 1. <hi>Becauſe it doth not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly appear that</hi> Geva <hi>was a Baſtard; for in all the Records that I cite, ſhe is called Earl</hi> Hugh<hi>'s Daughter; and in one of them, ſhe calls</hi> Randle <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter <hi>her Coſin; which makes it probable, that ſhe was legitimate; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſince you do not find by any Deed, Record, or Author whatſoever,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100342:20"/>that ſhe is at any time called a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer to the firſt Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though we find her not called Baſtard in expreſs terms; yet we find it implied in an Author contempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by certain and ſure conſequence, which I believe can never be fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe words of</hi> Ordericus <hi>p.</hi> 787.— <hi>Richardus pulcherrimus puer, quem ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ex</hi> Ermentrude <hi>filia</hi> Hugonis <hi>de Claro monte genuit, conſulatum tenuit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by which words you are not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but he might as well mean, that</hi> Richard <hi>was the only Son, as well as the only Child begot on</hi> Ermentrude: <hi>for there is no neceſſity to take the word (ſolum) adverbially: neither is it marked as an Adverb in</hi> Ordericus <hi>his Book; though it be ſo in mine:</hi> —<hi>And though he tells us,</hi> p. 522. <hi>that. E pellicibus plurimam ſobolem utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:100342:20"/>ſexus genuit; yet be ſaith not that</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va <hi>was one of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer to the Second Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will not perhaps be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of his meaning; for he ſaith not, <hi>Quem ſolum filium,</hi> as you interpret him; but indefinitely, <hi>Quem ſolum ex</hi> Ermentrude <hi>genuit:</hi> So that, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ſolum,</hi> be underſtood adverbial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (which certainly to moſt men will here ſeem more proper) or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you take it for a Noun, you can make no more of it in Engliſh than thus, <hi>Richard</hi> a beautiful youth, whom only Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> begot on <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentrude,</hi> &amp;c. For whether we En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh it, whom only he begot; or whom he only begot, it retains the ſame ſenſe; for if any other perſon, either Son or Daughter, were begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on <hi>Ermentrude</hi> by Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> then could it not be ſaid that <hi>Richard</hi> was only begot on <hi>Ermentrude;</hi> and can any man now imagine from this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>Ordericus,</hi> that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had any other Iſſue by <hi>Ermentrude</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:100342:21"/>but only <hi>Richard?</hi> So that if we believe <hi>Ordericus,</hi> who living in that Age, knew the truth better than we can now, <hi>Geva</hi> was no Daughter by <hi>Ermentrude;</hi> and by certain conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence muſt be one of the baſe Iſſue mentioned by <hi>Ordericus,</hi> though he names none in particular: and ſhe cannot be by any former Wife (your old Subterfuge) becauſe Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had never any other Wife; which ought either to be proved by you, or elſe no good reaſon appears to the contrary; and then ſure the Deed proving <hi>Geva</hi> had Lands given in free Marriage, the precedent holds and proves, that Lands in thoſe elder Ages paſſed with Baſtards in free Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, whom they owned for their own Children, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>quod erat demonſtrandum.</hi> I add further, that if <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> had a Daughter by <hi>Ermentrude</hi> (for you your ſelf confeſs and expound the words of <hi>Ordericus</hi> to be, that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had no other Son) what advantage is it for your purpoſe, unleſs <hi>Geva</hi> was that Daughter, and ſo ſhe be legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate?
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100342:21"/>See now, then <hi>Geva</hi> muſt needs be Siſter of the Whole-blood to Earl <hi>Richard,</hi> and by conſequence ſole Heir to her Brother of all the Earldom; as you interpret <hi>Ordericus:</hi> and ſo I leave it to every Readers Judgement; and then by your own Argument, ſhe ſhould have had the Earldom.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Page</hi> 45.</p>
            <p>Then you proceed to my Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>That if</hi> Geva <hi>had been Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, her Iſſue ought rather to have ſucceeded into the Earldom of</hi> Cheſter <hi>then</hi> Randle de Meſchines, <hi>after the death of</hi> Richard <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter: <hi>That doth not at all follow (ſay you) becauſe it is poſſible the Earldom of</hi> Cheſter <hi>at that time (as most times Earldoms anciently were) might be entailed on the Heirs-Males only, and then the Male Line being extinct, why might not the King confer it as well upon</hi> Randle de Meſchines <hi>who was a near kinſman, as on a ſtranger, which later courſe is alſo uſual at this day;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100342:22"/>and it is very probable, that the Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was entailed on the Heirs-Males onely; for</hi> James York <hi>in his union of honour,</hi> p. 105. <hi>ſays, That this</hi> Randle <hi>was made Earl by grant of King</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>the First; and if ſo, it came not to him by Deſcent; and ſo all that I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, you ſay, is fully anſwered. But if it had been ſo, that the Earldom had been to deſcend to the Heirs general; if</hi> Geva <hi>was Daughter of</hi> Hugh Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus <hi>by another Wife beſides</hi> Ermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude, <hi>then the Earldom of</hi> Cheſter <hi>would have deſcended from Earl</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard <hi>to</hi> Randle de Meſchines <hi>by his Mother, being Aunt of the whole blood to</hi> Richard, <hi>and not his Siſter</hi> Geva, <hi>or her Iſſue, they being but of the Half-blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer to the third Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let any ingenious Reader obſerve, whether, any ſubſtantial Anſwer be here given at all; you ſay it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the Earldom was then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed on the Heirs Males onely; but will you argue upon poſſibilities, to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100342:22"/>prove a thing <hi>de facto?</hi> but ſuppoſe it were ſo entailed, why ſhould not the King have conferred it on the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of <hi>Geva,</hi> before <hi>Randle de Meſchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> that being the Iſſue of a Siſter, and <hi>Randle</hi> the Iſſue but of an Aunt? or why may you think that the King (though he gave it to <hi>Randle</hi>) did not give the honour and Lands unto him as in whom was the greateſt right to have it? but to this you give no Anſwer at all; but we find not that the Iſſue of <hi>Geva</hi> ever moved for it. The true reaſon being that her Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle was not good; but had ſhe been Legitimate, it is more then proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſhe would have looked after the obtaining of ſo great an inheritance, yea and obtained it too before <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle:</hi> Nay, had ſhe been but of the Half-blood (which is your old and onely Subterfuge) ſhe would by all probability have buzled hard for ſo great an Eſtate in thoſe Ages, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe had loſt it; but you are now come to an excellent way of arguing by ifs, and ands, and poſſibilities; by which means Anſwers may be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100342:23"/>made to any thing even to eternity; but if you would ſubſtantially prove <hi>Geva</hi> to be of the Half-blood, then muſt you prove <hi>Hugh Lupus</hi> to have another Wife before <hi>Ermentrude,</hi> and <hi>Geva</hi> to be the Daughter of that very Wife; I would fain have you but to prove that ever he had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wife by any Hiſtorian, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; this would be ſomething; but what you here ſay, is nothing; and then you Inſtance, that the Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Cheſter</hi> probably was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed on the Heirs Males onely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſes <hi>James York</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Randle Meſchines</hi> was made Earl by the Kings grant; and if ſo (ſay you) it came not to him by deſcent; who muſt grant it him, but the King? what doth hinder, but the King gave it to him as one who by deſcent had moſt right to it, although he was not the direct Heir Male of Earl <hi>Hugh,</hi> but of another Family, yet a near Kinſman by marriage? And therefore muſt now come in by a Grant; yet for all this, no neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that the Earldom was entailed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100342:23"/>at that time on the Heirs Males onely.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Page</hi> 46.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now you come to ſhow me a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent (which I deſired) where ever the Heirs of an Aunt inherited before the Heirs of a Siſter, both legally born,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And now you will ſhew me where an honour in ſuch a caſe came to the Heirs of the younger Siſter, and not to the Heirs of the elder Siſter; which is full as much (ſay you) as if it were done in the caſe of a Siſter and an Aunt; and you Inſtance out of</hi> Birds <hi>Treatiſe of Nobility,</hi> p. 96. <hi>in the Caſe of</hi> Raufe <hi>Lord</hi> Cromwell, <hi>being a Baron-by Writ, died without Iſſue leaving two Siſters and Co-heirs:</hi> Elizabeth <hi>the eldeſt Married Sir</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Nevill, Joane <hi>the younger Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Sir</hi> Hunt Bourcher: Bourcher <hi>was called to Parliament as Lord</hi> Cromwell, <hi>and not sir</hi> Thomas Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:100342:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer to the fourth Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bird</hi> indeed alledgeth this Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the place cited; where he tells us before, That the Queſtion or point [that is, whether a Barony by Writ may deſcend to the Heirs Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males or no?] is ſomewhat perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by means of difficult Preſidents; and now in this place he ſaith (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to compound the Controverſy) that it is obſerved, that ſome Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents do prove that Baronies by Writs have deſcended unto Heirs Females, whoſe Husbands have been called to Parliament, whether in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of themſelves, or in regard of their Wifes, it matters not: and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, out of the Precedents it is to be obſerved, That the King is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs at liberty to call to Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, whom he ſhall think moſt meet in his Princely Wiſdom, as his Majeſties Progenitors in former Ages have obſerved; and then he brings in the Caſe of the Lord <hi>Cromwell</hi> before mentioned: thirdly, it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100342:24"/>that if a Baron by Writ dye without Heir Male, having Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or Siſter, or other (who can challenge the Lands of ſuch Baron deceaſed) the Title of ſuch Heir Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male hath been heretofore allowed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now the Caſe comes as near to the Caſe of <hi>Geva,</hi> as an Apple to an Oyſter; for let any rational man be Judge, whether the King by his Pretogative Summoning by his Writ to Parliament the Husband of the younger Siſter and Co-heir, before the Husband of the elder Siſter and Co-heir, both of them ſharing the Lands equally, be any thing to the Point of <hi>Geva,</hi> or to ſatisfie why ſhe ſhould not have had both the Earl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and all the Lands thereof, had ſhe been legitimate, and by conſequence ſole Siſter and Heir to her Brother <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> And in this Caſe of the Kings Writ propoſed, yet you ſee the Siſters ſhared the Lands, as by right they ought to do; and ſo I ſhall paſs to your next Reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100342:25"/>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Page</hi> 48.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But now you come and ask me what I will ſay, if this Deed which I alledge to be made to</hi> Geva, <hi>will not at all concern</hi> Amicia; <hi>becauſe</hi> Cook <hi>upon</hi> Littleton, <hi>fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b. (which in your Book you have miſcited alſo by putting the Page for the Folio) tells us, that theſe words</hi> [in liberum maritagium] <hi>are words of Art, and ſo are neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required: As if a man give Lands to another with his Daughter</hi> in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nubio ſoluto ab omni Servitio, <hi>yet here paſſeth but an Eſtate for Life: And the words in the Deed to</hi> Geva <hi>are not</hi> in liberum maritagium, <hi>but</hi> in libero conjugio; <hi>and ſo are but like the words</hi> in Connubio ſoluto ab omni Servitio, <hi>which make but an Eſtate for Life; and ſo might be paſsed to a Baſtard or any other</hi> — <hi>and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you ſay, the Deed to</hi> Geva <hi>is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as if it intended onely an Eſtate for Life, there being no mention of her Heirs: and ſecondly, it is given to</hi> Geva <hi>alone, and not unto a Husband
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100342:25"/>with her; whereas that given to</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waringe <hi>with</hi> Amicia <hi>in free Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, mentioneth their Heirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Anſwer to the fifth Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though the Lord <hi>Cook</hi> ſay, <hi>That by theſe words</hi> in Connubio ſoluto ab omni Servitio, <hi>there paſſeth but an Eſtate for life;</hi> yet he ſaith not, <hi>That by theſe words</hi> in libero conjugio, <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth onely an Eſtate for Life:</hi> nor in Caſe the words had been <hi>in libero Connubio,</hi> he ſaith nothing of them; although you are pleaſed to ſay, <hi>That the words</hi> in libero Conjugio, <hi>are but like the words</hi> in Connubio ſoluto ab omni Servitio, <hi>which make but an Eſtate for Life.</hi> I think, Sir, you and I being no profeſſed Lawyers, had beſt to leave theſe things to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Law; and notwithſtanding the Criticiſm, I beg both your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and my Lord <hi>Cooke</hi>'s too if he ſhould have ſaid it (which I do not find that he doth) in this Caſe of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va;</hi> for the Lands in the Deed men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned did deſcend to her Heirs by
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100342:26"/>
               <hi>Baſſet:</hi> and even at this day it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Drayton-Baſſet,</hi> in diſtinction of other Towns called alſo <hi>Drayton;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Baſſets</hi> were anciently Lords thereof; and this very Deed was taken out of a Manuſcript in <hi>Arundel</hi>-houſe, wherein the old Deeds belonging to the <hi>Baſſets</hi> of <hi>Drayton-Baſſet</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire</hi> were enrolled about the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, as you may ſee it men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in my Book. Again you ſay, <hi>The Deed to</hi> Geva <hi>is worded as if it intended onely an Eſtate for Life; and is made to</hi> Geva <hi>her ſelf without the words [her Heirs] mentioned therein;</hi> where you are to take notice, that this Deed of the firſt <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Cheſter</hi> is but a Confirmation to his Coſin <hi>Geva</hi> of a former Deed, <hi>Sicuti Comes</hi> Hughes <hi>ei in libero Conjugio dedit;</hi> which Deed (may be) had the Land paſſed to her and her Heirs, or to her Husband with her and to their Heirs: But for certain, ſhe and her Heirs by <hi>Baſſet</hi> had the ſame Land, however Earl <hi>Hugh</hi>'s Deed did run: I add further to your Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100342:26"/>that it was intended but for Life, becauſe given to her onely without the word (Heirs): <hi>Cooke</hi> upon <hi>Littleton, fol.</hi> 21. <hi>b</hi> citeth <hi>Peter Saltmarſh</hi> Caſe, and <hi>Fitz Herbert de Natura Brevium, fol.</hi> 172. that Lands may be given by a Man to his Son in Free-marriage; and why not as well to his Daughter alone in Free-marriage? which words of Frank-marriage do of themſelves create an Eſtate of inheritance, as <hi>Cooke</hi> ſaith in the ſame Page. And now we have done with <hi>Geva;</hi> and I appeal to the indifferent Reader, whether my Reaſons alledged for her Baſtardy in my other Book, be by you in the leaſt taken off by any ſolid Anſwers or Reaſon to the contrary; although in your Book you brand me with an aſperſion of her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 50, 51.</p>
            <p>And now you come to the ſecond Reaſon alledged, <hi>To prove that</hi> Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia <hi>is legitimate; which you ſay hath its full ſtrength yet, and is not at all
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100342:27"/>weakened by any thing I have ſaid: For in my computation according to reaſonable ſuppoſitions it cannot be well affirmed, that</hi> Hugh Cyveliok <hi>was above ſeven or eight years, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, older then his Wife</hi> Bertred: <hi>But by your computation, you ſay poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he may be</hi> 26. <hi>or</hi> 27. <hi>years older: whoſoever will take pains to ſcan both our computations, will ſee which is more moderate and reaſonable: in yours you ſuppoſe</hi> Maud, <hi>Earl</hi> Hugh's <hi>Mother; to be born the ſecond year af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her Mothers Marriage; and</hi> Maud <hi>Married in the</hi> 16th <hi>year of her Age, and Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>born in the</hi> 17th <hi>year of</hi> Maud's <hi>Age which falls in</hi> Anno 1129. <hi>and ſo all in the utmoſt poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; and if we may compute by poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, as you do, I ſay Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>might be but four years older then</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; <hi>but if you will go by ſtrong pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities, that Earl</hi> Randle (<hi>Father of Earl</hi> Hugh) <hi>was Married by</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert <hi>Earl of</hi> Gloceſter <hi>unto</hi> Maude <hi>his Daughter, thereby to draw him to the Part of Queen</hi> Maud <hi>his Siſter, about the very year</hi> 1139. <hi>before which
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100342:27"/>time we find no mention in our ancient Hiſtorians of</hi> Randle's <hi>actings againſt King</hi> Stephen; <hi>but in that very year we do, and then by ſome of them ſtiled Son in Law to the Earl of</hi> Gloceſter; <hi>but not before that year, that I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: I ſay, if we reckon by utmoſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities, Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>could not poſſibly be above</hi> 16 <hi>or</hi> 17 <hi>years older then</hi> Bertred; <hi>but rationally we may imagine he was not ſo old by many years: and though your gheſſes may be a little in the dark, yet I think I am about the very time of his Marriage: ſo that if your Argument carry its full ſtrength, it is certainly but a little ſtrength, if any at all; it is but this: Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>was older then</hi> Bertred, Ergo <hi>he had a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Wife; and of your account, you ſay you may abate me ſeveral years, and yet Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>be a great deal older then his Wife: wherein you ſay true:</hi> but I can gather no ſuch quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of years in reſpect of his Age, reaſonably to ſuppoſe him to have had any former Wife.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:100342:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 52.</p>
            <p>The third and fourth Reaſons (you ſay) <hi>are onely urged as concurrent Proof with the Argument brought from the words</hi> in libero maritagio: <hi>So then your Achillean Argument failing, all the other fall to the ground; to which hath been ſpoken before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 52, 53.</p>
            <p>But yet you muſter up all your forces to ſtrengthen the third and fourth Reaſons for. <hi>Amicia: as</hi> Hugh Cyveliok's <hi>Counteſs being witneſs to the Deed of</hi> Amicia in libero marita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio <hi>[and yet you, that take no notice of the Law in ancient times from the Law of later Ages, and inſiſt ſo much upon Law, cannot but know a Wife is no good Witneſs either for or againſt her Husband, and yet both here and in ſundry other Deeds we find them put as Witneſſes to their Husbands Deeds:] alſo</hi> Raufe Manwaringe <hi>calling his Daughter</hi> Bertrede <hi>after the name of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100342:28"/>the Counteſs</hi> [<hi>methinks he ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have called her after the name of his former Counteſs, Mother of</hi> Amice, <hi>if Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>had had any ſuch Wife</hi>] <hi>alſo</hi> Roger Manwaringe <hi>in another Deed calling</hi> Randle <hi>of</hi> Cheſter <hi>and</hi> Lincolne <hi>his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle:</hi> Raufe Manwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe <hi>being with the Earl at</hi> Coventry <hi>and a Witneſs to his Charler to his Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes there: alſo</hi> Roger Manwaringe, <hi>and</hi> Henry de Audley <hi>who Married his Siſter, being Witneſſes to the Deed of</hi> Randle <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter <hi>and</hi> Lincolne, <hi>concerning the Abby of</hi> Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacres: Henry de Audley's <hi>being a Witneſs to the Deed of</hi> Robert de Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans <hi>(this is far fetcht) whoſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was one of the Siſters and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs to the aforeſaid Earl</hi> Randle: <hi>as alſo</hi> Rafe Manwaringe <hi>being a Witneſs to one Deed of</hi> Hugh Cyve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioks, <hi>and to three other Deeds of the ſaid Earl</hi> Randle: <hi>Theſe (ſay you) are ſuch circumſtances as ſhew a more great and conſtant intimacy between the ſaid two families, then probably would have been, if</hi> Amicia <hi>had been a Baſtard.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:100342:29"/>
            <p>To all which is eaſily anſwered, that being Witneſſes to Deeds argues no great intimacy with the Parties; and though the Judge in regard of his place were more converſant with the Earl, yet <hi>Amicia</hi> may be a Baſtard for all this: Let the Ingenious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der judge. The like multitude of Charters, or more, you may find, whereto <hi>Philip Orreby</hi> Judge of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> was Witneſs in like nature; and alſo many other. Gentlemen, as well as <hi>Roger Manwaringe</hi> and <hi>Henry de Audley:</hi> But I ſpeak not this to leſſen your Family, but to ſhow the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 54.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>Although I object that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in Hiſtories and Records Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards are called Brother, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle, Coſin, Son, and Daughter; you grant it to be true; but that (you ſay) was done either when Perſons came to be great, as</hi> Robert <hi>Earl of</hi> Gloceſter <hi>did; or elſe done by their Relations out of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. But I can hardly find one (you
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100342:29"/>believe) that I can certainly prove to be a Baſtard, or the Son of a Baſtard, who doth preſume in a Deed to call ſo great a Perſon as the Earl of</hi> Cheſter <hi>was, his Brother or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle, unleſs he came to be a very great Perſon himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed Precedents are ſcant; but ſome there be: What do you think of <hi>Ranulpho de Astbury nepote Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Ceſtriae;</hi> who is put the laſt of all the Witneſſes in the Deed, as you may ſee in the <hi>Addenda</hi> of my Book? Certainly he was but an ordinary Gentleman, nor Knight, nor Lord: But you will ſay, I cannot prove him a Baſtard; yet I ſhould be glad to find out his Extraction, if he were not: 'tis a ſhrewd preſumption.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now we ſhall come to another of like Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 54.</p>
            <p>Here you tell me, <hi>you believe</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Bacun<hi>'s Mother was not a baſe Daughter of</hi> Hugh Cyveliok, <hi>nor any Daughter of his at all; becauſe we find
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100342:30"/>in</hi> Monaſticon, <hi>part</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 267. <hi>in his Deed of the Foundation of</hi> Rouce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Priory <hi>in</hi> Staffordſhire, <hi>his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle</hi> Randle <hi>was living</hi> (<hi>where take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice he calls</hi> Randle <hi>Earl of</hi> Cheſter <hi>his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkle</hi>) <hi>and a</hi> William <hi>was then Archbiſhop of</hi> York, <hi>and</hi> R. <hi>then Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Cheſter; <hi>and there was neither Archbiſhop of</hi> York <hi>whoſe name was</hi> Will. <hi>nor Biſhop of</hi> Cheſter <hi>whoſe name began with</hi> R. <hi>in the time of</hi> Randle Blundevil; <hi>and therefore you think it was</hi> Randle de Gernoniis, <hi>that</hi> Bacun <hi>calls <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkle, and not</hi> Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Blundevil.</p>
            <p>But truly you are deceived in it: For it is true, as you obſerve, that there was no ſuch Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> called <hi>Will.</hi> nor Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter</hi> whoſe Chriſtian Name began with <hi>R.</hi> both living at one time, either in the time of <hi>Randle de Blundevil</hi> or <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle de Gernoniis,</hi> that I can find: nor was the Biſhop of <hi>Chester</hi> (being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Biſhop of <hi>Lichfield</hi> and <hi>Coventry</hi> at this time) then ſubject to the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of <hi>York,</hi> but <hi>Canterbury:</hi> Wherefore I do conceive the Roll,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100342:30"/>from whence the Deed in <hi>Monaſticon</hi> was written, is miſtaken in <hi>Wil.</hi> and <hi>R.</hi> and miſs-writ therein from the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Chart it ſelf; ſo that certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here is a miſtake: But that which is the greateſt certainty to guide us, is the body of the Deed it ſelf; which ſeems to be perfect and right; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he tells us, that he hath procured the Confirmation and Warranty of <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> his Unkle for the ratifying of that his Grant. And the very next Deed following in the Roll, and tranſcribed in the <hi>Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticon,</hi> is the Deed of <hi>Randle</hi> Earl of <hi>Chester</hi> with Confirmation and Warranty accordingly; whereunto <hi>Roger Lacy</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> is a witneſs, who only lived in the time of <hi>Randle Blundevil,</hi> and of no other Earl of <hi>Chester;</hi> as you may ſee it clearly proved among the Barons of <hi>Halton,</hi> in my Book; nor is there any other Deed of Confirmation and Warranty to be found by any Earl, ſave this; wherefore certainly it muſt be <hi>Randle Blundevil,</hi> whom <hi>Richard Bacun</hi> calleth Unkle in his own Deed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100342:31"/>of the Foundation of the ſaid Prio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and then muſt it neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that his Mother was the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok;</hi> and it is plain, ſhe was no Co-heir to <hi>Randle Blunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil:</hi> and it doth not in the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that <hi>Hugh</hi> had any other wife, ſave <hi>Bertred</hi> the Mother of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs: nor doth it appear, that ever ſhe had ſo much as any Land <hi>in libero maritagio;</hi> which you ſo much ſtand upon in the caſe of <hi>Amicia.</hi> And now let every man be Judge, whether I have aſperſed (as you call it) this Lady unjuſtly; and whether ſhe be not a Baſtard in the opinion of all impartial Readers: which word <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed,</hi> you might well have ſpared; for Aſperſion is when a man malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſeeks to throw dirt in anothers face unjuſtly; of which ſort of men I hope you do not judge me to be. But theſe matters fall unavoidably in my way; the truth whereof (as near as I can) I only do endeavour to find out.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:100342:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 57.</p>
            <p>And now you come to anſwer the Arguments and Reaſons which I bring to prove <hi>Amicia</hi> a Baſtard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> had no other Wife than <hi>Bercred,</hi> then <hi>Amicia</hi> muſt certainly be a Baſtard; for ſhe was not a Daughter of <hi>Bertred,</hi> as is grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on all ſides:</p>
            <p>But <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> never had any other Wife than <hi>Bertred;</hi> Ergo <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi> was certainly a Baſtard.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Minor</hi> is to be proved by the Affirmer; for <hi>oportet affirmantem probare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Anſwer to the first Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By this Rule</hi> (you ſay) <hi>I am as much bound to prove her a Baſtard, as you are bound to prove that</hi> Hugh Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veliok <hi>had a former Wife; becauſe I clearly affirm that, as you affirm the</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:100342:32"/>
            <p>
               <hi>My Reply to the first Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs what you ſay to be true; yet the Rule of the affirmative part to prove, in <hi>Logick</hi> alwayes holds true: for a Negative cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But I ſay further, that I have proved her a Baſtard by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, unleſs he had a former wife; for you muſt either deny the <hi>Major,</hi> or the <hi>Minor,</hi> or grant them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the affirmative part lies now on your part to prove.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your ſecond Anſwer to my first Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> pag. 58.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A leſs proof will ſerve by many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to prove a thing done long ſince, than will be requiſite to prove a thing done lately; the like reaſon is in all Caſes of Antiquity; So that if you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prove her called Daughter, being ſo long ſince, ſhe ought to be preſumed legitimate, unleſs the contrary do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; for the proving ſhe was not by</hi> Bertred, <hi>doth not prove ſhe was a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100342:32"/>but only proves ſhe was either a Baſtard, or elſe by a former wife; and our Law at this day is, That a Baſtard ſhall not be allowed to be proved a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard but in his life time; why ſhould</hi> Amice <hi>then be charged with Baſtardy ſo many hundred years after her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Reply to your ſecond Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where you ſay, if you only prove her called a Daughter, being ſo long ſince, ſhe ought to be preſumed legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate till the contrary appear: I ſhall grant it; but here are many ſtrong reaſons to the contrary; and you are now to anſwer the Argument in hand; and for your aſſerting, that my proving ſhe was not by <hi>Bertred,</hi> doth not prove her a Baſtard, but proves ſhe was either a Baſtard, or elſe by a former wife; this is not to the Point; for the Argument runs, If he had no other wife but <hi>Bertred,</hi> and ſhe no Daughter to <hi>Bertred,</hi> then certainly if ſhe be a Daughter, and ſo called, ſhe muſt needs be a Baſtard:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:100342:33"/>and as to the point of Law you urge, that a man cannot be proved a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard but in his life-time to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of an Eſtate; becauſe the dead perſon cannot anſwer to the excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Yet though the Law allows not this in Pleadings, what hinders but Baſtardy may be proved by Hiſtory or Argumentation, after the Parties death? Suppoſe in a Regiſter-Book I ſind ſuch a Baſtard Chriſtened one hundred years ago, may not I juſtly call that Perſon a Baſtard, whom I find ſo Regiſtred? The law may make a Baſtard legitimate by Act of Parliament: as we find in the caſe of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi>'s Children by <hi>Katha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine Swynford,</hi> 20. <hi>Ric.</hi> 2.1397. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all intents and purpoſes in the Law, <hi>excepta dignitate Regali,</hi> whereby they ſhall inherit as if they had been lawfully born; but may not we therefore call them Baſtards? No Law can make a Baſtard once born, to be no Baſtard in nature; for <hi>quod factum eſt ſemel, infectum reddi non patest.</hi> And to this your ſecond An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100342:33"/>I believe it is clearly evinced without further demonſtration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your third Anſwer to my firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> p. 59.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You conceive that the paſſing of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices</hi> in libero maritagio <hi>with</hi> Amice, <hi>doth abſolutely prove that ſhe was a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Child, and by conſequence muſt be by a former wife; and that ſhe would not have been ſtiled as ſhe is in the Deed, unleſs ſhe had been a legitimate Daughter: and you cite</hi> Spelman<hi>'s quoting</hi> Couſtum. du Normand. <hi>Art.</hi> 77. <hi>Quoties enim agitur de honore vel commodo filiorum; appellatione filio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non comprehenduntur Baſtardi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Reply to your third Anſwer to my first Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is what before you have ſaid over and over again; and hath before been anſwered by me: But I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that neither the naming of her Daughter in the Deed, nor paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Services with her <hi>in libero ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritagio,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:100342:34"/>doth at all prove her legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate; for I have before told you, and ſhall entreat the judicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to look back where I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpoken of it; That in thoſe ancient Ages the word daughter was frequently uſed without the addition of Baſtard, both in old Deeds and Hiſtories: nay rarely or never was it otherwiſe uſed even to Baſtards as well as Lawful Iſſue; whereof are ſundry Examples, as is well known to all ſuch as are skilled in Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: and by your own Argument, if ſhe were not called his Daughter, no eſtate of inheritance could have paſſed by the Deed, though ſhe were a Baſtard; becauſe hereby ſhe is own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be of his Kindred and Bloud; and that Lands have paſſed <hi>in libero maritagio</hi> to ſome ſuch, who are known to be Baſtards, though not ſo named; whereof I have ſhewed a Precedent of thoſe Ages in my Book, which is not refelled yet by any ſolid Reaſon to the contrary, as the ingenuous Reader may perceive <hi>ſupra,</hi> pag. 18. of this Book, <hi>&amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inceps.</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:100342:34"/>And what you add out of <hi>Spelman,</hi> is little to the purpoſe, that in caſes of honour and profit diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was then made, that by the appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Sons, Baſtards are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the Cuſtoms of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy:</hi> what then this ſuppoſeth that in other caſes and formerly by the appellation of Sons, Baſtards were comprehended: This makes direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt you: and you know what <hi>Spelman</hi> ſaith in the very words next following—<hi>That the ancient Northern People admitted Baſtards to ſucceed in their Inheritance; and that</hi> William <hi>the Conquerour was not aſhamed of that Title, who began his Letter to</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan <hi>Earl of</hi> Little Britaine <hi>(as he did many others)</hi> Ego <hi>Willielmus</hi> cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento <hi>Baſtardus.</hi> But what is all this to the anſwering of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or proving <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> to have had a former Wife? only you would have the words <hi>in libero mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagio</hi> to prove <hi>Amice</hi> abſolutely legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate: this is all the Anſwer you give to the Point; and this will not do it, as is before proved; whither
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:100342:35"/>I have referred the Ingenious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your fourth Anſwer to my first Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> p. 60, 61.</p>
            <p>And here you ſay, that <hi>if all must be Baſtards, if we could not tell who were their Mothers, nor directly prove their Fathers married, we might then conclude most Perſons Baſtards; and ſo you could frame my own Argument against me thus; —If</hi> Roger Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waringe (<hi>who lived about</hi> 1119.) <hi>had no wife, then</hi> William, Randle, <hi>and</hi> Wido (<hi>Sons of the ſaid</hi> Roger) <hi>were certainly Baſtards: But</hi> Roger Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waringe <hi>aforeſaid had no wife;</hi> ergo, <hi>&amp;c. Now if this Argument against</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micia <hi>will hold, it would alſo hold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst theſe three Children of</hi> Roger, <hi>and ſo against all others in like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:100342:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>My Reply to your fourth Anſwer to my first Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you argue well; and I ſay to your <hi>Minor,</hi> that <hi>Roger</hi> had a Wife, though we yet know not who ſhe was: and this appears certainly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lands deſcended from heir to heir. But I frame my affirmative part more formally thus: —If the Son and Heir of <hi>Roger</hi> ſucceeded by deſcent in his Inheritance, then <hi>Roger</hi> had a wife; But the Son and Heir of <hi>Roger</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by deſcent in his Inheritance; this is apparent by the enjoyment thereof from heir to heir; <hi>ergo, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> had a wife.</p>
            <p>If you deny the Sequel of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor,</hi> I prove it thus—No Baſtard can ſucceed in the Inheritance without a ſpecial ſettlement; <hi>ergo,</hi> if the Son and Heir of <hi>Roger</hi> ſucceeded by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent in the Inheritance, then <hi>Roger</hi> muſt needs have a Wife; and nothing appears here of any ſpecial ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And ſo you ſee, the Argument re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted is anſwered.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:100342:36"/>
            <p>Now if you could prove by like Reaſon, that <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> had a former wife before <hi>Bertred,</hi> it would be ſome Anſwer; but the paſſing of Lands <hi>in libero maritagio</hi> in that age, is no certain Argument of Legitima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; for then I confeſs you would prove <hi>ex conſequenti</hi> Hugh Cyveliok muſt needs have another wife; which is the chief conteſt between us; for all the reſt of your Arguments for her Legitimacy, are little material, and not ſolid. Now you repeat this often over and over again, where you have as oft been told, that Land in thoſe former Ages did paſs to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards <hi>in libero maritagio;</hi> whereof I have given you one Precedent; which neither yet hath been, nor (as I conceive) can be rationally an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: Beſides the words of <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> implying the ſame; and the Term of Baſtard, was, for certain, uſually omitted in the Deeds and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of thoſe times; and the own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them for Daughters in their Deeds, poſſibly that the Lands might paſs to their Heirs, as owning them
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:100342:36"/>to be of their Kindred and Bloud, are all Reaſons againſt the Deed; that it doth not prove her legitimate: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the Caſe of <hi>Amice,</hi> and the three Sons of <hi>Roger</hi> alike; for there is nothing that appears againſt them, either to prove or ſuſpect them for Baſtards, as there is in the caſe of <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce;</hi> for here is a wife of <hi>Hugh Cyveliok</hi> certainly recorded; a Son and four Daughters carrying away all Earl <hi>Hugh</hi>'s Lands: alſo Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known to have ſundry Baſtards; and <hi>Amice</hi> having no ſhare of any of the Lands whatſoever, though the Eldeſt Daughter of Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate by a former wife, as you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: all which carries more than a bare probability that <hi>Amice</hi> was a Baſtard. And therefore here is a neceſſity of proving a former wife, which I firmly believe Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had: And to this you ſay, the falling of the great Eſtate to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs, was the cauſe of their being taken notice of by the Hiſtorians of that Age; which Inheritance (ſay you) came to them as Siſters to <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:100342:37"/>of the whole bloud (although you prove not that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> ever had any other wife) and <hi>Amice,</hi> you ſay, was of the half bloud; but you prove it not. And you ſay further, that <hi>Ric. Bacun</hi>'s mother was not any Child of Earl <hi>Hugh:</hi> But that ſhe was Earl <hi>Hugh</hi>'s Daughter, I have clearly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. So that all theſe ſtrong Preſumptions of the Baſtardy of <hi>Amicia,</hi> I leave to the Reader, to judge whether any thing hath been ſubſtantially ſaid by you to evince any mans impartial judgment to the contrary, or that hath at all anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my firſt Argument.</p>
            <p>And now you come to anſwer my ſecond Reaſon or Argument againſt <hi>Amicia,</hi> which I framed thus, — Whatſoever is given in frank-marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, is given as a Portion; now the releaſe of the Service of one Knights Fee in Frank-marriage (according to your Deed) ſeems not a competent portion for a legitimate Daughter of the Earl of <hi>Cheſter;</hi> eſpecially for the eldeſt Daughter: for ſo ſhe muſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:100342:37"/>be, being of the firſt venter, which is always more worthy then the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and we find the other Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Married to four of the greateſt Perſons in <hi>England,</hi> which is a ſtrong Preſumption that <hi>Amice</hi> was a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard: methinks <hi>res ipſa loquitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Anſwer to my ſecond Argument,</hi> Pag. 64, 65.</p>
            <p>To which you Anſwer, <hi>That it will not hold; for though what is given in Frank-marriage, be given in conſideration of a Marriage, yet it cannot properly be called a Portion</hi> — <hi>&amp;c. and further you ſay, that if ſhe had been but a Baſtard, yet being a Baſtard of ſo great a Perſon, ſhe would have had a great deal more given her then theſe ſervices</hi> — <hi>But you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, if this Deed of Earl</hi> Hughe's <hi>had been lost, I would not have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that Sir</hi> Raufe Manwaringe <hi>had had any thing with</hi> Amicia: <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then it would not have appeared: which is a ſtrange way of arguing, about things that were done ſo long
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:100342:38"/>ſince. And if this be a good Reaſon, you wonder I do believe that Earl</hi> Hugh <hi>had any Portion with his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs</hi> Bertred, <hi>becauſe (for ought you yet know) it doth not appear that he had. Again you ſay to my alledging how the other four Siſters were Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, that you have anſwered that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And though I ſay, that if</hi> Amice <hi>had been legitimate, ſhe being of the firſt venter, would have been more worthy then thoſe of the ſecond</hi> — <hi>yet in this Caſe, when there be Siſters of two Venters, and the Brother be of the ſecond Venter, and the Siſters claim as Heir to their Brother, then the Siſters of the Second Venter ſhall be preferred before thoſe of the first Venter: and then you cloſe your Anſwer in telling me that you do not underſtand why I call this gift of Earl</hi> Hugh's <hi>(as I do in two ſeveral places) a Releaſe of the ſervice of one Knights-Fee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:100342:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>My Reply to your Anſwer to my ſecond Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto I Reply, to what is neceſſary to be replied unto herein; firſt, whereas you ſay, <hi>That if ſhe had been a Baſtard, yet being the Baſtard of ſo great a Perſon, ſhe would have had a great deal more then thoſe ſervices given her:</hi> it may be ſo; what then? here is no reaſon that we can ſuppoſe ſhe had any more Lands, neither any Money anſwerable to the eldeſt Daughter of the Earl legitimate, for the other Siſters had all the Lands of Earl <hi>Hugh;</hi> and we find not any more Lands bought by Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> for <hi>Amicia;</hi> but you perceive, that if this Deed had been loſt, I would not have believed, that Sir <hi>Raufe Manwaringe</hi> had had any thing with <hi>Amicia;</hi> which (ſay you) <hi>is a ſtrange way of arguing about things done long ſince:</hi> and how do you know, that I ſhould have believed that he had had nothing at all? but you would have me ſuppoſe, that <hi>Amicia</hi> had as much
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:100342:39"/>Money as any of the Co-heirs; I am ſure ſhe ought to have had ſo, had ſhe been legitimate; but I believe neither you, nor I, nor any other Perſon can imagine ſo: And if the Deed mentioned had been utterly loſt, I ſhould not then have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that there was ſuch a Deed: for how can any man believe that which he never knew, nor heard of? <hi>de non Apparentibus, &amp; non Exiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, eadem est ratio:</hi> and though I may well ſuppoſe, that Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> had a good Portion with his Wife; becauſe he was ſo great a Perſon, yet neither I nor any perſon (that knows it not) can well gheſs what it was. And had it only appear'd by Record, That Sir <hi>Raufe Manwaringe</hi> had Married the Earl of <hi>Cheſter's</hi> Daughter, and nothing appeared what was given, I ſhould then have believed ſhe had had a greater Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion given her, then what is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in your Deed: but the Deed appearing, and ſo ſmall a Portion mentioned therein, makes it more ſtrong that <hi>Amicia</hi> was a Baſtard.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:100342:39"/>And laſtly, that you may underſtand, what I mean by calling Earl <hi>Hugh's</hi> grant a Releaſe of the ſervice of one Knight's Fee; becauſe the grant to <hi>Raufe Manwaringe</hi> with <hi>Amicia</hi> in Free Marriage is only the ſervice of <hi>Gilbert</hi> Son of <hi>Roger,</hi> to wit, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of three Knights Fees, he and his Heirs doing to Earl <hi>Hugh</hi> and his Heirs the ſervice of two Knights Fees: ſo as the Earl hereby reſerves to himſelf the other two Knights Fees as formerly; but now remits the ſervice of the third Knights Fee: nor is it the grant of any Land, but of ſervices incident to Land; but what all this is to the taking of the Argument propoſed, I leave to the Reader to Judge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now you come to my third and laſt Reaſon, which I did put as a probable concurring Reaſon, That all the Ancient Hiſtorians of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who lived in that Age, and have Recorded the other Daughters
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:100342:40"/>and Co-heirs; yet not one of them mentioning <hi>Amicia:</hi> which proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly one or other would have done, had ſhe been a legitimate Daughter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Anſwer to the third Reaſon, Page.</hi> 67.</p>
            <p>Whereunto you ſay, <hi>You conceive there is no weight at all in it; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I am ſo ſenſible, that I conceive it not evincing; nor do thoſe Antient Hiſtorians take upon them to give an account of all the Children of Earl</hi> Hugh, <hi>but onely of the Heirs of</hi> Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Blundevill: <hi>and yet (you ſay) this Reaſon is as ſtrong as my first Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Reply.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do confeſs I urged it but for a probable Reaſon; and yet (you ſay) it is as ſtrong as the firſt Reaſon: Then you might have done well to have anſwered the firſt better: whereunto I am ſure you have made no ſubſtantial Anſwer as yet: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I appeal to all indifferent and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:100342:40"/>Readers, who ſhall read this Book. And for the probability of this, you ſay, <hi>That the Hiſtorians take not upon them to give an Account of all the Earls Children, but the Heirs of Randle;</hi> but do you find that they have left out any of his legitimate Children, except this whom you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe legitimate?</p>
            <p>And then you tell me, <hi>Mr.</hi> Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>hath mentioned</hi> Amicia, <hi>though not among the Co-heirs, yet without the brand of a Baſtard:</hi> you know well, he is but of very late ſtanding, and not an Hiſtorian Contemporary with <hi>Amicia:</hi> and ſo you and I do now mention her. And then you tell me over again (which I have before Anſwered) that thoſe Judges and Heralds that have ſeen your Deeds (of which I have heard, but I am ſure I yet know not who they be, nor ever ſaw any thing atteſted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any of their hands, nor their Reaſons nor grounds for their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) and you mention Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi> in particular, for whom I have ever had a great eſteem as a diligent
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:100342:41"/>ſearcher of Antiquities, all which you again and again affirm to be of your Opinion, that <hi>Amicia</hi> was legitimate; but becauſe I have before ſpoken of this <hi>Supra, pag.</hi> 10, 11. I ſhall onely ask here, what weight can be drawn from this? ſome Perſons are of that Opinion, <hi>Ergo</hi> it is ſo: whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels have erred, unleſs like the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, you will ſay <hi>The Pope cannot err:</hi> And perhaps thoſe Perſons you mention, never heard what is to be ſaid againſt that Opinion: whereas it were but equal that in conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Opinions, both ſides ſhould ſhow what could be ſaid <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con</hi> both together; which hitherto (for ought I know) onely one Party hath privately put the Caſe, as he pleaſeth; I have often told you, I would have you confute me with Reaſon, not Opinions: for one man may be of one Opinion, and another man of another Opinion; but it is firm Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which muſt ſway every mans Judgment.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:100342:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 69.70, 71, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, <hi>you put down two Deeds, wherein Sir</hi> Raufe Manwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe <hi>Juſtice of</hi> Cheſter <hi>is ſubſcribed Witneſs before the Barons of</hi> Cheſhire; <hi>for which you think it will be difficult to give a Reaſon, if</hi> Amice <hi>were a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſay, it will not be diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult at all to give a Reaſon: and much more eaſie, then to give a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why <hi>Amice</hi> ſhould be no Baſtard, becauſe Sir <hi>Raufe Manwaringe</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Subſcribed before the Barons of <hi>Cheſhire.</hi> The Reaſon I give is this, that antiently in thoſe Ages, the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice was put ſometimes before the Barons, and ſometimes after; and ſometimes after the Conſtable, and Dapifer, and before the reſt of the Barons, as it happened: for proof, ſee the Deed in my-Book making the Baron of <hi>Halton,</hi> the prime Baron, <hi>pag.</hi> 160. where the Juſtice comes after all the Barons; alſo in the Deed
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:100342:42"/>of Earl <hi>Randle</hi> to his Barons, <hi>pag.</hi> 162. where the Juſtice comes next after the Conſtable and Dapifer, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other Barons; ſee alſo in my Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 130, 131. two Deeds made by <hi>Hugh Cyveliok:</hi> In the one, the Juſtice is put after the Conſtable and Dapifer: In the other, the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is put before them; many other like examples may be produced elſe where: I will appeal herein to Mr. <hi>Dugdale,</hi> or to any Antiquary in <hi>England:</hi> and conſidering the great uncertainty of Subſcription of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in old Deeds, ſometimes put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one before another, in one Deed, and again putting the ſame Perſon after the other in another Deed; ſometimes putting <hi>Domino</hi> prefixed before the names of ſome Perſons in one Deed, and omitting the word <hi>Domino</hi> before the names of the ſame Perſons in another Deed, whereof I have ſpoken, <hi>pag.</hi> 5, 6. in the beginning of this Book. I ſay, had you well conſidered or obſerved theſe things, it was not worth your labour to have added thoſe three or
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:100342:42"/>four leafs in the cloſe of your Book. And now I appeal to all Readers, whether thoſe Grounds and Reaſons alledged in my former Book againſt the legitimacy of <hi>Amicia,</hi> as alſo to prove the Baſtardy of thoſe two other Ladies (as you call them) <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va,</hi> and the Mother of <hi>Richard Bacun,</hi> be evinced by any ſolid Anſwer or Reaſon given yet to the contrary.</p>
            <p>And ſo I take my leave for ever of this Trivial Controverſie; but ſhall ever remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Mobberley <date>May 15. 1673.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your affectionate Coſin and very humble Servant <hi>PETER LEYCESTER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:100342:43"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader,</head>
            <p>I <hi>Have here in the end of this Book an opportunity to Rectifie ſome Omiſſions and Errours in my former Book, which eſcaped me through miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>information of others, and deſire thee to pardon and amend them, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 206. <hi>after the last line but two, ſhould have followed this</hi>—</p>
            <p>— Alſo another <hi>John Brereton,</hi> ſon of <hi>George Brereton</hi> of <hi>Aſhley</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> was Baptiſed at <hi>Bowdon</hi> the 20th day of <hi>June,</hi> 1576. he was afterwards Sir <hi>John Brereton</hi> Knight, the King's Serjeant at Law in <hi>Ireland;</hi> he died without Iſſue, whoſe-Widow Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston:</hi> Sir <hi>John</hi> left all his Perſonal Eſtate (which was great) to his Widow, and <hi>Caius</hi>-Colledge in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> where he was educated, and to <hi>Randle brereton</hi> his youngeſt Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; which <hi>Randle</hi> lived in <hi>London</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:100342:44"/>and Married, and had Iſſue by his Wife a Daughter Married to Mr. <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> of <hi>Gloceſterſhire,</hi> and a Son called alſo <hi>Randle Brereton</hi> who hath an Eſtate in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> and is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Iſſue Male, or Heir-male, of all the Family of the <hi>Breretons</hi> of <hi>Aſhley</hi> now ſurviving, 1672.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 210. <hi>line</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>Where theſe words [<hi>With the little Fields above, lying up to</hi> Aſton <hi>Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi>] are totally to be expunged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 214. <hi>line</hi> 18, 19.</p>
            <p>Where it is ſaid — [<hi>Daughter and ſole Heir of Sir</hi> Henry Willoughby] Read — <hi>Daughter and ſole Heir to her Mother, and Daughter and Co-heir to her Father Sir</hi> Henry Willoughby; <hi>for Sir</hi> Henry <hi>had three Daughters and Co-heirs:</hi> Anne; <hi>after the death of Sir</hi> Thomas Aſton, <hi>Married Mr.</hi> Gray <hi>younger Son of the Earl of</hi> Stamford; <hi>ſhe was by the firſt Wife of Sir</hi> Henry; <hi>he had alſo two Daughters by his ſecond Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:100342:44"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ibidem page</hi> 214. <hi>line</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>Read — <hi>He was Loyal to his Prince, and raiſed a Regiment of Dragooners for the King at his own coſt and charge, and was a Gentleman of good Parts: but was unfortunately</hi> — &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 223.</p>
            <p>The 6, 7, 8. lines are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punged totally.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 233. <hi>line</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>There it is ſaid — <hi>Maud</hi> Married Sir <hi>Robert Nedham</hi> of <hi>Shenton</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire</hi>] which words are to be expun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 315. <hi>line</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Where it is ſaid — <hi>George Venables</hi> of <hi>Agden</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> one ſmall Tenement] Read — <hi>George Venables</hi> of <hi>Agden</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> three ſmall Tenements in <hi>Mere,</hi> in poſſeſſion of <hi>William Occleſton, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:100342:45"/>Bower,</hi> and <hi>Peter Chorton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 315. <hi>line</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>It is there ſaid — <hi>Edward Allen</hi> of <hi>Rosthorne,</hi> one ſmall Tenement in <hi>Mere</hi>] Read thus — <hi>Edward Allen</hi> of <hi>Rosthorne,</hi> one ſmall Tenement in <hi>Mere</hi> in poſſeſſion of <hi>Henry Hunt,</hi> and two parts of <hi>John Occleston's</hi> Tenement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 316. <hi>line</hi> 18, 19.</p>
            <p>Where it is ſaid — <hi>Geffrey Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> Gentleman, hath lately bought the <hi>Shaw-houſe</hi> in <hi>Millington,</hi> from <hi>Millington</hi> of <hi>Millington</hi>] Read thus, — <hi>Geffrey Cartwright</hi> Gentleman, hath the <hi>Shaw-houſe</hi> in <hi>Millington,</hi> which <hi>Richard Cartwright</hi> his Father bought of <hi>Thomas Shaw,</hi> 1646. which Land was formerly <hi>John Wilkinſon</hi>'s; and <hi>Shaw</hi> came to it by Marriage.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:100342:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 326. <hi>lin.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Where it is ſaid — <hi>Came to</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Cholmondeley] Read thus — <hi>Came to</hi> Francis Cholmondeley <hi>for his life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 327. <hi>line</hi> 10, 11.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid — <hi>Thomas Brooke,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Son married <hi>Jane</hi> Daughter of one <hi>Weſton</hi> of <hi>Sutton</hi> nigh <hi>Frodſham,</hi> Tenant to <hi>Warburton</hi> of <hi>Arley</hi>] inſtead whereof read — <hi>Thomas Brooke,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Son, married <hi>Jane Woodfen,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Richard Woodfen</hi> of <hi>Sutton</hi> near <hi>Frodſham</hi>-Bridge: Her Mother afterwards married <hi>William Weſton</hi> of <hi>Aſtmore</hi> in <hi>Halton;</hi> ſo that <hi>Weſton</hi> was but her Stepfather.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 327. <hi>line</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Where it is ſaid — <hi>Richard Brooke,</hi> third Son of Sir <hi>Richard;</hi> Profeſſor of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> died at <hi>Boughton</hi> nigh <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> without Iſſue, <hi>anno Dom.</hi> 1667.]
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:100342:46"/>put out the words <hi>[without Iſſue]:</hi> for he had Iſſue by <hi>Sarah</hi> his former wife, daughter of Judge <hi>Warburton</hi> of <hi>Hifferton</hi>-Grange in <hi>Weverham</hi> Lordſhip; although he had no Iſſue by <hi>Anne</hi> his latter wife, the Widow of <hi>Edward Holland</hi> of <hi>Denton</hi> in <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> and Daughter of <hi>Edward Warren</hi> of <hi>Pointon</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 334. <hi>line</hi> 33, 34.</p>
            <p>Where it is ſaid —<hi>Which Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel</hi> Margery <hi>his Wife ſurviving erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with the two Monuments therein for her ſelf and Husband,</hi> anno Dom. 1456.] inſtead whereof, read thus, —<hi>Which Chappel this</hi> Randle <hi>cauſed to be erected, with the two Monuments therein for himſelf and wife,</hi> an. Dom. 1456.] <hi>for</hi> Margery <hi>died before him,</hi> to wit, 27. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>and he died</hi> 35. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 280. <hi>line</hi> 44.</p>
            <p>Where in the Margin it is ſaid — <hi>Corrupte pro ſaltuariis, id est,</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtars]
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:100342:46"/>Read —<hi>Corrupte pro ſaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus, aut ſaltatoriis, id est,</hi> Deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaps.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 335, <hi>line</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Where is omitted as followeth— Agnes, <hi>another Daughter of</hi> John Manwaringe, <hi>Eſquire, married Sir</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Nedham <hi>of</hi> Crannach <hi>in</hi> Cheſhire <hi>Knight, and afterwards of</hi> Shenton <hi>in</hi> Shropſhire; <hi>which</hi> Shavington, <hi>vulgo</hi> Shenton, <hi>was eſtated on him by Judge</hi> Nedham, <hi>who purchaſed the ſame: And this Match appeareth by a blewiſh Marble-ſtone or Monument, in the Chancel of</hi> Adderley-<hi>Church in</hi> Shropſhire; <hi>whereon are the Pictures of the ſaid Sir</hi> Robert Nedham <hi>and Dame</hi> Agnes, <hi>and ſeven Sons and two Daughters; as alſo an Inſcription (all of them in Braſs) as followeth,</hi> —</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here lieth buried under this Stone the Bodies of Sir</hi> Robert Nedeham <hi>Knight, and Dame</hi> Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <hi>his Wife, Daughter of</hi> John Manwaringe <hi>of</hi> Pever <hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> which
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:100342:47"/>ſaid</hi> Robert <hi>deceaſed the</hi> iiij. <hi>day of</hi> June; <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1556. <hi>And the ſaid</hi> Agnes <hi>deceaſed the</hi> 11. <hi>Day of</hi> May, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1560.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 345. <hi>line</hi> 36.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>[where]</hi> is to be expun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: for the Lady <hi>Mary Cholmondeley</hi> died at <hi>Vale-royal,</hi> which ſhe purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and gave it to <hi>Thomas Cholmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deley</hi> her fourth Son, and his Heirs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 361, <hi>line</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>Where it is ſaid —<hi>Died unmarried,</hi> 1653.] Read—<hi>Was never married; he drowned himſelf the ſixth day of</hi> July, 1653.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 374. <hi>line</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Read Sir <hi>Amos Meredeth</hi> Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. <hi>a.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 376. <hi>line</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>Where is omitted—<hi>Hugh Toft,</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:100342:47"/>another Son, Parſon of <hi>Alderley,</hi> and after of <hi>Stopport,</hi> 8. Hen. 4. <hi>lib. C. fol.</hi> 229. <hi>T. num.</hi> 40, &amp; 42.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1402. 3. Hen. 4.29. Novem. <hi>Nobilis Vir</hi> Johannes le Manwaringe <hi>Dominus de</hi> Stockport <hi>praeſentat ad Eccleſiam de</hi> Stockport <hi>Hugonem</hi> de <hi>Toft Capellanum, poſt mortem</hi> Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi <hi>de</hi> Bagiley <hi>ultimi Rectoris,</hi> lib. B. p. 12. d.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 381. <hi>line</hi> 28.</p>
            <p>Where is omitted —<hi>alſo another Son, called</hi> William Leyceſter, who <hi>died without Iſſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 392. <hi>line</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>Where ſhould follow thus—<hi>The ſaid</hi> Robert Venables <hi>bought all the Demain-Land, and alſo</hi> Wood<hi>'s Farm with the Mills, called</hi> Cranage-<hi>Mills. But the Tenements were ſome of them bought by the Tenants themſelves, and ſome of them by others.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:100342:48"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 437. <hi>line ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Add there thus — <hi>Only</hi> Dodleſton <hi>remains yet to</hi> Cheſhire, <hi>and</hi> Marleſton <hi>nigh</hi> Eccleſton, <hi>and</hi> Claverton <hi>and</hi> Lache <hi>nigh</hi> Cheſter; <hi>which were all part of</hi> Atiscros-Hundred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Amendments, Reader, will ſet thee ſtraight in the Peruſal of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Book; together with the correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the</hi> Errata<hi>'s of Printing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the great negligence of the Printer; which are now mentioned and rectified by a diſtinct Page at the end of the ſaid Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Farewel.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100342:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
